Guide to the John Felstiner Papers
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
John Felstiner papers
circa 1960s-1990s
SC1113
Felstiner, John.
7.5 Linear feet (6 boxes)
This collection contains Felstiner's course materials and other Stanford professional files; files related to two of his publications; captions from exhibits related to four poets; and restricted files (comprised of confidential student Information).
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Information about Access
Restricted files closed until January 1, 2060. Otherwise the collection is open for research; materials must be requested at least 48 hours in advance of intended use. Audio-visual materials are not available in original format, and must be reformatted to a digital use copy.
Biographical/Historical note
John Felstiner received his A.B. (1958) and Ph.D (1965) from Harvard. In between, he spent three years on the USS Forrestal in the Mediterranean. Felstiner came to Stanford in 1965. His first book, The Lies of Art: Max Beerbohm's Parody and Caricature (1972), has to do with parody as a critical, creative, and comic form. Since then his teaching and writing have dealt mainly with modern poetry. Teaching North American poetry in Chile in 1967-68 led to Translating Neruda: The Way to Macchu Picchu (1980), which won the Commonwealth Club of California Gold Medal, and to an ongoing concern with the practice of literary translation, along with its interpretive, creative, and theoretical implications. The British Comparative Literature Association gave 1st and 2nd prizes to his Pablo Neruda and Paul Celan translations.
During the 1970s John developed critical approaches to poetry by civilians and soldiers from the Vietnam era, and after teaching at the Hebrew University in Israel (1974-75), he began studying the literature, art, photography, and music that emerged from the European Jewish catastrophe. His book on the German-speaking Jewish poet, Paul Celan: Poet, Survivor, Jew (1995), was a Finalist for the National Book Critics Circle award and the MLA's James Russell Lowell prize, and won the Truman Capote Prize for Literary Criticism.
Selected Poems and Prose of Paul Celan (Norton, 2001) won the Modern Language Association's biennial Lois Roth Award for Translation of a Literary Work, the American Translators Association's biennial award for German translation, PEN West's prize for literary translation, and was runner-up for American PEN's translation award, the Helen and Kurt Wolff Prize, and the British Society of Authors' Schlegel-Tieck prize.
John co-edited the Norton anthology, Jewish American Literature (2000). He has held Guggenheim, Rockefeller, NEH, and NEA fellowships, taught literary translation twice at Yale, and is a member of the American Academy of Arts and Sciences.
This Dust of Words, John's memoir of his brilliant late-Sixties student Liz Wiltsee, inspired a documentary film that is being screened at various festivals: thisdustofwords.com.
After retirement, Mary Felstiner and John taught two Stanford courses, to undergrads and adults, on "creative resistance." That is, writings such as graffiti, letters, poetry, diaries, journals, chronicles, also art and photography, and music of all sorts, all emerging from victims throughout Nazi-occupied Europe.
In writing Can Poetry Save the Earth?: A Field Guide to Nature Poems (2009), on poetry and environmental urgency, John worked at the Stanford Humanities Center and the Yaddo, Macdowell, Millay, Djerassi, Mesa Refuge, and Jentel artists colonies. American Poetry Review ran six essays from this book, and NPR's Morning Edition featured it:. http://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=102795472. Poets House in Manhattan focused on his book's theme in '09-'10. Having received a foundation grant, John is currently visiting high schools around the country to share the environmental awareness that poems can awaken in the next generation. 'Save the Earth' Poetry Prize is offered in 2012 for 11th & 12th grade high school students.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains course materials and Stanford professional files, which include: course syllabi, lecture notes, and research files, mostly related to Jewish American literature, the Holocaust, Vietnam, and poetry. There are some correspondence and other professional files related to general Stanford or departmental matters. The writing series includes files related to two of Felstiner's publications: The Lies of Art: Max Beerbohm's Parody and Caricature, and Jewish American Literature: A Norton Anthology, which Felstiner co-edited. Exhibit captions contain text from exhibits about poets Paul Celan, Franz Kafka, Max Beerbohm, and Pablo Neruda. The restricted series contains materials separated from the course materials files due to sensitive student information such as grades, student identification numbers, or other identifiying information. Files are restricted for 75 years from date of creation.
Arrangement note
This collection is divided into four series: Course materials and other Stanford professional files; Writing; Exhibit captions; and Restricted files (comprised of confidential student Information).
Access Terms
Felstiner, John.; Stanford University. Department of English.; American poetry- -20th century- -History and criticism; American poetry--20th century.; Literary criticism; Poetry, Modern; Poetry, modern--20th. century.; Poetry.; Translating and interpreting.
Collection Contents
- Course Materials and Stanford professional files
  - Words (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Words (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Holocaust Music - Still songs to sing, transparencies (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Johnny Payne (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - IHUM 037B - Literature into Life (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - IHUM 037B - Literature into Life, handouts (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - 164A - Texts (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Responses to "Seeing the 2nd Sex"/37B, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - IHUM (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - 164A - Articles (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - 164A - Bibliography (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - 164A - Originals (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - 164A (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Learning Magazine (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - 164A - Holocaust, notes (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - 140A (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Poets, A - G (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Poets, G - L (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Poets, M - Z (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Holocaust Poetry, A-Z (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Egl 140A - Creative Resistance and the Holocaust, 2009 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - American Poetry (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - SOC 41/PS 181, 1976-1977 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Egl 60/160A - American Jewish Writing, 1977-1978 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Skidmore - Jewish Studies, texts, notes (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Jewish American Lit - 161D, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Holocaust clippings (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Celan - Multiple Copies (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Holocaust Materials, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Holocaust Clippings (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Holocaust Clippings, etc. (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - 164B Holocaust Materials recent, 1999-2000 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Jewish American Lit - transparencies (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Headnotes (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - 117-119: Lecture notes (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Modern British Comic Writers (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Freshman English (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Humanities Center (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Crow - Women Poets (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Women Writers - Dialogues, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Yeats, Eliot (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Jewish Studies, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Modern British Comic Writers - Notes (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Early Poetry Classes (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Modern Brit. Comic, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - 358E/188B/269D/369 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - American Jewish Lit - Early notes (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Jewish Studies (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - 160C Ruth Wisse, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Chimen Abramsky Hist 125B, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Hebrew H. U. Jerusalem, 1974-1975 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - 259C Contemporary Hebrew Poetry (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Holocaust and Memorial/Education Fund, 1996 Oct 15 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - I. A. Richards course at Harvard, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Letters from Stanford people (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - SULAIR Annual Report, 1972-1973 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Glosses - The Stanford Undergraduate Literary Journal (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - On One Foot (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Kadima (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Rich (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Paley (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Ozick (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Malamud (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Howe (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Ginsberg (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Vietnam Articles (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Trilling (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Singer (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Roth (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Vietnam - Stanford Observer, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Vietnam (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Vietnam - notes (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - 154B Master Cop's (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Vietnam - correspondence (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Feldman (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Engl 50 - American Poetry (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Engl 50 - American Poetry - handouts, poems (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - 350B (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - 150 - Lecture notes (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - 150 etc - Modern Poetry - Materials, various (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - 259B North American and Latin American Poetry (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Engl [?] Handouts (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - 60/160 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - 188P (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Wiesel (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Misc Course Material (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Environment Course Reader (Box 4, Folder 28)
- Writing
  - Jewish American Literature (Norton Anthology)
    - Norton (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Norton (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Norton (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Norton Anthology Jewish American Literature - Reviews and letters (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Translations - Rilke; Bibliography (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Jewish American Lit (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Teaching the Jewish Experience in America: Units and Resources (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Norton - Bibliographies (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Jewish American Lit - bios (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Jewish Experience in America (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Beerbohm
    - Photo - Cecile Beaton (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Correspondence, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - A Christmas Garland, mss/tss (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - Beerbohm (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - Beerbohm (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - Beerbohm Photos (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - Beerbohm - Illustration copies (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - Caricatures of Twenty Five Gentlemen (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - J.F. Talk on Beerbohm (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - Photographs - Caricatures (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - Photographs - Caricatures (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - Caricatures (Box 5, Folder 5)
- Exhibit Captions
  - Neruda (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Beerbohm (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Kafka (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Celan (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Restricted Files
  Restricted 75 years from date of creation.